Guide to the Oral History Project Documenting Yale University
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Gray, Hanna Holborn, 2008 May 20
  Hanna Holborn Gray received a B.A. from Bryn Mawr College in 1950 and a Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1957. After teaching history at the University of Chicago, in 1972 she was appointed Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences at Northwestern. She served as Successor Trustee of the Yale Corporation from 1971 to 1974, when she resigned to become the first woman Provost of Yale, and Professor of History. In 1977-78, she served as Acting President of Yale. Gray was then appointed President of the University of Chicago, the first woman to serve as the chief executive of a major coeducational university. She retired in 1993 and became professor emeritus. In 2007 she served as Chairman of the Board of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.
  Architecture, Modern; Yale University -- Employees -- Labor unions; Coeducation; Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1919-1988; Gray, Hanna Holborn; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Edelman, Marian Wright; Whitney, John Hay, 1904-1982; Yale University. Office of the Provost; Berliner, Robert W., 1915-2002; Mory's Association (New Haven, Conn.); Yale College (1887- ); Yale Corporation
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Hackman, Judith, 2009 January 29
  Judith Hackman has held administrative posts at Yale since 1971 when she joined the Office of Institutional Research. She served as its director for five years. In 1987 she was appointed Associate Dean of Yale College. From 1995 to 1998 she was the Director of Corporate and Foundation Relations and Assistant to the Provost for three years. In the Graduate School she has served as director of the Teaching Fellows program and Dean of Assessment. She also served as Dean of Administrative Affairs. She earned an undergraduate degree at the University of Illinois, a master's degree in educational research at Southern Connecticut State College, and a doctorate from the University of Michigan.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Holcombe, Terry, 2008 April 1
  Former Yale Vice President for Development and Alumni Affairs, 1982-1998.
  From 1964 to 1972 Holcombe was Executive director of ACCION, a private micro loan development program in Latin America and in 1974-1976 served as vice president of Whittier College. He was Executive director of The Campaign for Yale 1976-1979; and Vice president for university development and alumni relations at Columbia University 1979-1981. Holcombe returned to Yale in 1981 as the University's first Vice President for Development and Alumni Affairs. He was responsible for all development activities, including the Alumni Fund, the Association of Yale Alumni, Alumni Records and other alumni relations activities. Holcombe planned and directed the $1.7 billion capital campaign completed by Yale in l998. He holds a 1957 BA and an honorary MA from Yale University and a MA from the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Krauss, Judith, 2007 July 2
  Dean, School of Nursing, 1985-1998
  Judith B. Krauss received her nursing education and a BS from Boston College in 1968 and a MS in Nursing from Yale in 1970. She remained at Yale starting as an instructor in psychiatric nursing rising through the ranks to associate professor when she was appointed acting dean of the nursing school in 1985. In the same year she was appointed dean and professor of nursing serving until 1998. She is currently serving as professor of nursing, Master of Silliman College, and Chairman of the Council of Masters.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Lamar, Howard Roberts, 2007 February 2
  University President, 1992-1993; Yale College Dean, 1979-1985; History professor.
  Howard Lamar received a B.A. from Emory University in 1944. He entered the Yale Graduate School Department of History and received his PhD in 1951. From his first Yale teaching appointment in 1949, he was promoted through the ranks: as instructor, 1949-1954; assistant professor, 1954-1959; associate professor, 1959-1964; professor, 1964-1970; Coe Professor, 1970-1987; Sterling Professor, 1987-1994; and Sterling Professor us, 1994-. He served as department chairman and director of graduate studies in history in the 1960s; and as Director, division of Humanities, 1972-1974. From 1979-1985 he was Dean of Yale College. After the resignation of President Schmidt, Lamar served as university president in 1992-1993.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 39)
- LaPalombra, Joseph, 2010 November 11
  Joseph LaPalombara received his B.A., from the University of Illinois in 1947 and his PH.D. in comparative politics from Princeton University in 1954. After teaching at Michigan State University, Yale appointed him professor of political science in 1964. He was chair of the department for two terms, director of the Institution for Social and Policy Studies, and chairman of the Council on Comparative and European Studies. His research is centered on the relationship between public policies, global corporations, and the flow of foreign direct investment to less-developed countries.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 39a)
- Lytton, Bernard, 2007 August 27
  Professor Emeritus of Surgery and Residential College Master
  Dr. Lytton was educated in England and appointed Assistant Professor, Urology at Yale in 1962. He served as associate professor, 1967-70, professor since 1970; chief, section of urology, 1971-87; as Donald Guthrie Professor of Surgery, 1988-2000; Master, Jonathan Edwards College, 1987-97; and Director of the Koerner Center since 2003. Dr. Lytton performed the first kidney transplant at Yale in 1967.
  Yale University -- Employees -- Labor unions; Hospice care; Wald, Florence, 1917-2008; Jonathan Edwards College (Yale University); Yale University. School of Medicine; Berliner, Robert W., 1915-2002; Yale University. School of Nursing; Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Levin, Richard C., 1947-; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Malkiel, Burton
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Marcus, Ruth B., 2010 August 4
  - Interview
    - Use copy
  - Transcript
    - Use copy
- Morgan, Edmund S., 2007 July 11
  Yale History Professor
  Edmund Morgan received his B.A. in 1937 and his Ph.D in 1942 from Harvard. He began his teaching career at Yale in 1954 as a Visiting Lecturer and was appointed professor of history in 1955. In 1965 he became a Sterling Professor, and in 1986 became emeritus professor. He is the author of dozens of books on colonial American history. The recipient of many awards for his teaching and writing, President Clinton awarded Morgan the 2000 National Humanities Medal.
  Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1919-1988; Levin, Richard C., 1947-; Broude, Henry W.; Wright, Mary Clabaugh, 1917-; Pierson, George; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Gray, Hanna Holborn; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Kagan, Donald; Yale University. Dept. of History; Spence, Jonathan D.; Turner, Frank M. (Frank Miller), 1944-2010
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Patton, Curtis L., 2007 May 1
  Patton received his undergraduate degree from Fisk and his doctorate from Michigan State University. He taught at Rockefeller University 1967-1970. In 1970, he was appointed Professor in Epidemiology of Microbial Diseases at the Yale School of Public Health. He is the Director of International Medical Studies and Chair of the Committee on International Health. Amongst his numerous awards and achievements, Dr. Patton received the Edward A. Bouchet Leadership Award in 2004.. Dr. Patton has been Chair of the YSPH Minority Affairs Committee since it was established in 1992 and has served on many significant committees on minority issues.
  Apartheid; Divestment; Women college teachers; Public health; African Americans -- Education; Diversity in the workplace; Gray, Hanna Holborn; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Yale Corporation; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Wellington, Sheila; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Yale University. School of Medicine; Webster, Noah; Rosenberg, Leon
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Pease, David, 2007 November 27
  Retired Art School Dean, Art School Professor
  David Pease was educated at the University of Wisconsin where he received the degrees of BS in 1954, MA in 1955, and MFA in 1958. He taught at the Tyler School of Art at Temple University from 1960 to 1983, where he served as dean from 1977 to 1983. He was then appointed Dean of the Yale School of Art and served until 1996. He continued to teach painting until his retirement in 2000.
  Yale University -- Employees -- Labor unions; Women college teachers; Diversity in the workplace; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Broude, Henry W.; Levrant de Bretteville, Sheila; Ryerson, Ellen; Suttle, Lloyd; Yale Corporation; Yale University. Art Gallery; Yale University. School of Art
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Pelli, Cesar, 2008 December 10
  Dean School of Architecture, 1977-85
  Cesar Pelli was born in Tucumán, Argentina where he received an Architecture Degree in 1950. In 1954 he earned a Master of Science degree at the University of Illinois. As a professional architect he also worked for Eero Saarinen. After several appointments as visiting professor he was appointed Dean of the Yale School of Architecture in 1977. At the same time he established the firm Pelli Clarke Pelli in New Haven. His work has been widely published and exhibited, with eight books dedicated to his designs and theories. In 1995, the AIA awarded Cesar Pelli its Gold Medal. He has designed several buildings and additions for Yale including the Malone Engineering Center and the Boyer Center for Molecular Medicine.
  Architects; Campus planning; Architecture; Women college teachers; Diversity in the workplace; Broude, Henry W.; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Yale University. School of Architecture; Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1919-1988; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Gray, Hanna Holborn
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Pollitt, Jerome, 2008 January 30
  Yale Graduate School Dean, 1986-91; Classics professor.
  Jerome Pollitt received his B.A., from Yale in 1957 and PH.D. from Columbia University in 1963. Yale appointed him an instructor in the Classics department in 1962 and promoted him to assistant, to associate, and to full professor of Classical Archeology and History of Art in 1973. He is one of few Yale professors who has served as chair of two departments -- classics (1971-72 and 1975-77) and history of art (1981-84). Pollitt became a Sterling Professor in 1995 and professor emeritus in 1999. He served as Dean of the Graduate School, 1986-91.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Ponet, James
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Prown, Jules D., 2007 June 25
  Yale History of Art Professor; founding director, Yale Center for British Art.
  Jules Prown, Paul Mellon Professor Emeritus History of Art, received his PhD at Harvard in 1961and began his Yale teaching career that same year: A noted art historian, especially of material culture, he served as Curator of the Garvan Collection, Yale Art Gallery; and founding Director of the Yale Center for British Art, 1968-76. He later served as Acting and Interim Director in 1993 and 1994. In 1995 a symposium was held in his honor at Yale, and in 2005 he was honored with the DeVane medal for teaching.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Rae, Douglas W., 2007 December 5, 2008 January 10
  Professor Rae received a B.A. from Indiana University in 1962 and a Ph.D. from the University of Wisconsin in 1966. He joined the Yale faculty in 1967 and became a full professor in 1974. Rae is the Richard Ely Professor of Political Science and Management and is affiliated with the Institute for Social and Policy Studies, and the Committee on Urban Studies. He is a specialist in the political economy of cities, electoral politics, political ideology, and power relations. A political scientist and member of the Yale faculty since 1967, he took leave in 1990 and 1991 to serve as chief administrative officer of the City of New Haven under John Daniels, the city's first African-American mayor.
  - Interview (part 1), 2007 December 5; 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Interview (part 2), 2008 January 10; 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript (part 1), 2007 December 5; 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Transcript (part 2), 2008 January 10; 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Ruddle, Frank H., 2009 June 10
  Frank Ruddle received a B.A. from Wayne State University in 1953 and a Ph.D. from UC Berkeley in 1960. He was appointed to the Yale faculty in 1961 and became a full professor in 1972. Ruddle served as chairman of the biology department at Yale for two terms, first beginning in 1977 to 1982 and again from 1988 to 1992. As a cellular biologist studying the genome, his career coincided with the explosion of genetics and its understanding that has revolutionized medical science. He was a founding member of the Human Genome Organization (HUGO) formed in 1988 to solve problems of gene mapping and to deal with the ethical problems of gene experimentation.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Scully, Vincent, 2011 August 24
  - Interview
    - Use copy
  - Transcript
    - Use copy
- Simon, John, 2007 December 19
  Yale Law School Deputy Dean, 1985-1990; founding Director, Yale Program on Nonprofit Organizations, 1977-82.
  John Simon received his B.A., from Harvard in 1950 and LL.B from the Yale Law School in 1953. From 1953-58 he served as an assistant to the General Counsel, in the Office of the Secretary of the Army and practiced law in New York. Yale appointed him associate professor of law in 1962 and full professor in 1967. In 1975 he was appointed Lines Professor at the Yale Institution for Social and Policy Studies. He has served as deputy dean and acting dean of the law school, and acting chairman of the Center for the Study of Education. Simon pioneered in developing courses in nonprofit and philanthropy law and in elementary and secondary education law.
  Yale University -- Faculty; Women college teachers; Diversity in the workplace; Investments -- Moral and ethical aspects; Yale Law School; Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1919-1988; Gray, Hanna Holborn; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Yale University. Institution for Social and Policy Studies. Program on Non-Profit Organizations; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; Lindblom, Charles Edward; Yale Center for the Study of Education; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Goldstein, Abraham; Yale University. Institution for Social and Policy Studies; DiMaggio, Paul
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Singer, Maxine, 2008 August 6
  Yale Corporation Fellow, 1975-90, Successor Trustee
  Maxine Singer graduated from Swarthmore College in 1952 and received a PhD from Yale in 1957. In 1994, Yale awarded her an Honorary Doctor of Science degree. She is a leading molecular biologist and science advocate and has made important contributions to the deciphering of the genetic code and to the understanding of RNA and DNA. Singer was the third woman to serve on the Yale Corporation. From 1988 to 2002, she was president of the Carnegie Institution of Washington.
  Strikes and lockouts; Divestment; Biochemistry; Science -- Study and teaching; Yale University. School of Management; Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1919-1988; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Gray, Hanna Holborn; Yale Corporation; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Edelman, Marian Wright; Fruton, Joseph S. (Joseph Stewart), 1912-2007; Madden, John; Swenson, David; Yale University. School of Nursing; Altman, Sidney
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Skinner, Brian J., 2009 February 4
  Brian J. Skinner, who was born and raised in Australia, received a B.S. degree from the University of Adelaide in 1950, and a Ph.D. in 1954 from Harvard University. Yale appointed him professor of geology in 1966 and professor of geology and geophysics in 1968. He served as department chairman from 1967 – 1973. He is the Eugene Higgins Professor of Geology. Skinner's research interests include the origin and distribution of mineral deposits.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, computer file (DOC) (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Skinner, Catherine, 2008 April 11
  H. Catherine Skinner received a B. A. from Mount Holyoke College, an M.A. from Radcliffe Harvard in Mineralogy, and a Ph.D. from Adelaide University in Australia. She came to Yale in 1966 with her husband Brian J. Skinner, now a professor of geology & geophysics. Skinner served as Master of Jonathan Edwards College, 1977-82. She was the second woman to be appointed master, other than Katherine Lustman who completed her husband's term as Master of Davenport College; and the first to serve a full term. [Rosemary Stevens served as Master of Jonathan Edwards for only one year, 1974-75.] As of 2011, Skinner is still teaching and researching full time. Her major interest is in biominerals, especially bone mineral.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Spence, Jonathan D., 2009 May 5
  Jonathan Spence came to Yale in the fall of 1959 as a Clare-Mellon Fellow, after graduating from Cambridge University and serving in the British army. He then entered the Yale Graduate School and received a Ph.D. degree in 1965, when he joined the Yale faculty. Spence became the George Burton Adams professor of history in 1976 and Sterling Professor of History in 1993. He retired from full-time teaching in 2008. One of the world's leading experts on Chinese history and culture, he was selected by the National Endowment of the Humanities to deliver the 2010 Jefferson Lecture in the Humanities (considered the most prestigious honor the federal government bestows for achievement in the humanities). The author of more than a dozen books, his most famous work, The Search for Modern China (1990, rev. 1999), became a New York Times bestseller and continues to be a standard text on Chinese history from the 17th century.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Stevens, Jerald
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Streets, Frederick J. "Jerry", 2007 May 22
  University Chaplain 1992-2007
  Rev. Jerry Streets received a B.A. from Ottawa University in 1972; an MDiv from Yale in 1975; an MSW in 1981 and DSW in 1997 from Yeshiva University. After graduating from Yale, he served as pastor of the Mount Aery Baptist Church in Bridgeport, CT for seventeen years. In 1987, he was invited to teach at the Yale Divinity School, as an adjunct faculty member. He taught at Yale until 1992 when he was appointed University Chaplain, the first African American and the first Baptist to hold the position.
  Globalization; Religious education; Diversity in the workplace; Yale University. Chaplain's Office; Yale College (1718-1887). Church of Christ; Yale University. Divinity School; Highsmith, Martha; Levin, Richard C., 1947-; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Dwight Hall (Yale University); Yale University. Undergraduate Multi-Faith Council
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Tirro, Frank P., 2007 June 22
  Music School Dean, 1980-1989
  Frank Tirro received his Bachelor of Music degree from the University of Nebraska, his Master of Music degree from Northwestern, and his PhD degree from the University of Chicago. Before coming to Yale in 1980, Tirro served as Chairman of the music department at the University of Chicago and Dean of the Music School at Duke University. After completing his service as Dean of the Yale Music School in 1989, he continued to serve as professor of music, specializing in both the history of jazz and music of the Renaissance.
  Asian Americans -- Education; African Americans -- Education; Women college teachers; Yale University -- Employees -- Labor unions; Yale Corporation; Yale College (1887- ); Yale University. Office of the Provost; Goodman, Benny, 1909-1986; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Yale School of Music; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Levin, Richard C., 1947-; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Broude, Henry W.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Trachtenberg, Alan, 2009 June 17
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Trachtenberg, Betty, 2009 February 11
  Betty Trachtenberg began her Yale career in 1975 as an assistant in the admissions office. She developed the Eli Whitney Students Program for students of non-traditional age or background and directed summer term admissions and freshman affairs. She was dubbed the "Landlady of the Old Campus" for the attention she paid to every aspect of freshman residential life. Trachtenberg is also referred to by the students as the Dean of Sex, Drugs, and Rock'n'Roll. She served as Dean of Undergraduate Affairs for twenty years under five deans and retired in the spring of 2007.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 80)
- Trillin, Calvin, 2009 October 14
  Calvin Trillin received a B. A. from Yale in 1957, and an honorary M.A. from Yale in 1988. He served as chairman of the Yale Daily News and joined the staff of The New Yorker in 1963. He also writes for The Nation and Time. Major themes include his family, food, and travel. He served as a Yale Corporation Fellow from 1988 to 1994.
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Wheeler, Robert, 2007 June 27
  Yale Professor Emeritus of Engineering and Applied Science
  Robert Wheeler graduated from Lehigh University with a B.S. in physics in 1950. After receiving his doctorate at Yale in 1955, he was appointed to the faculty, becoming a full professor of physics and applied science in 1966. He chaired the Yale Department of Engineering and Applied Science from 1971 to 1974. From 1975 - 1978, he was Director, Division of the Physical Sciences. In 1996, he was named the Harold Hodgkinson Professor of Engineering and Applied Science. In his research and teaching he explores the relationship between physics and technology. He also served as director of graduate studies in the Faculty of Engineering
  - Interview, 1
    - Use copy, 1
  - Transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1, Folder 85)
- Wilkinson, John A., 2007 January 30
  Secretary of the University, 1981-1987 June.